Guide to the Henry Howard Kessler papers, 1912-1968.
Kessler, Henry Howard papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Henry Howard Kessler papers, 1912-1968.
3016
Henry H. (Henry Howard), Kessler, 1896-1978.
1.6 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, printed material, scrapbooks, diaries, publications.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection includes personal correspondence with Dr. Kessler's wife, Jessica Winnick Kessler, 1936-1960, 1942-1945 (bulk); his son Sanford, 1943-1945; and friends and acquaintances, 1918-1967; business correspondence pertaining to the Kessler Foundation, 1952-1958; scrapbooks and loose clippings; programs; miscellany documenting his travels, work and awards, 1928-1963; photographs showing his patients and colleagues, ca.1930-1945; diaries and notebooks, ca. 1947-1949; and copies of a number of Kessler's published works, 1925-1968.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Henry Howard Kessler (Cornell University Class of 1916, M.D. 1919) was an orthopedic surgeon and a medical administrator. He served the United Nations as international consultant on rehabilitation of amputees and people with congenital birth defects. He was a captain in the U.S. Navy, 1941-1945. He founded and directed The Kessler Institute for Rehabilitation, West Orange, New Jersey. He died in 1978.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection includes personal correspondence with Dr. Kessler's wife, Jessica Winnick Kessler, 1936-1960, 1942-1945 (bulk); his son Sanford, 1943-1945; and friends and acquaintances, 1918-1967; business correspondence pertaining to the Kessler Foundation, 1952-1958; scrapbooks and loose clippings; programs; miscellany documenting his travels, work and awards, 1928-1963; photographs showing his patients and colleagues, ca.1930-1945; diaries and notebooks, ca. 1947-1949; and copies of a number of Kessler's published works, 1925-1968.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Kessler, Henry H. (Henry Howard), (Henry Howard), 1896-1978.; Kessler, Jessica Winnick.; Kessler, Sanford.; Kessler, Jessica Winnick; Kessler, Sanford; Kessler Foundation.; Kessler Institute for Rehabilitation.; Kessler Institute for Rehabilitation
Subjects:
Medicine.; Orthopedics.; Physical therapy.; Orthopedists.; Surgeons.; Medicine; Orthopedics; Orthopedists; Physical therapy; Surgeons
Form and Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.; Programs (documents).; Photographs.; Diaries.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Scrapbooks, Clippings, Programs, Menus, etc.
Series III. Photographs
Series IV. Diaries and Notebooks
Series V. Works by Kessler
Series VI. Works about Kessler
Series VII. Education Mementos
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Subseries Ia. Letters to Jessica Winnick Kessler
    - Correspondence, Jan. 15 1936, Sep. 26-27 1938, Aug. 20 - Oct. 15 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1942-10-20-1943-01-17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1943-01-25-1943-03-08 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1943-03-13-1943-04-25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1943-05-02-1943-05-31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1943-06-01-1943-06-28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1943-07-03-1943-08-12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1943-10-19-1943-12-15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1943-12-18-1944-01-14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1944-01-17-1944-06-19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1944-09-11-1944-12-21 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1944-12-27-1945-04-23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, Apr. 23 1945 - May 1 1945, May 22-24 1950, Jun. 30 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subseries Ib. Letters Exchanged Between Sanford Kessler and His Father
    - Correspondence, 1943-01-17-1945-10-20 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Subseries Ic. Correspondence Pertaining to the Kessler Foundation
    - Correspondence, 1952-10-07-1953-05-27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1953-06-01-1954-05-06 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1954-08-24-1955-09-29 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1955-10-18-1956-06-19 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1956-09-21-1957-08-30 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1957-10-04-1958-07-28 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Subseries Id. Other Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1918-12-25-1949-09-03 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, Dec. 9 1953 - Jun. 7 1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series II. Scrapbooks, Clippings, Programs, Menus, etc.
  - Subseries IIA. Loose Papers
    - Loose Papers, 1943-10-1945-12 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Clippings, Primarily Mare Island Naval Hospital
    - Loose Papers (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Menus, Hunterian Society Lectures papers,
    - Loose Papers, 1945-1962 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Loose Papers, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      South Pacific; postcards; menus; poem; SPAEF Vol. 1, no. 3; Dec 3 1942 and Aug 16 1942 Medical Officers watch list
    - Loose Papers (Folder 42)
      Miscellaneous notes on foreign opinion of the United States; famous humanists; Commencement Address at Albertus Magnus College by Charles McKerr Parr; passover sermon, "This is the Pacific."
  - Subseries IIb. Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook A: American Physician's Club Trip to Europe - pp. 1-12, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Contains letters, programs, tickets, photos, postcards, souvenirs
    - Scrapbook A pp. 13-24, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Scrapbook A pp. 25-37, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Scrapbook A pp. 38-50, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Scrapbook A pp. 51-63, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Scrapbook B, 1935, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Clippings, program, photos, letters
    - Scrapbook C, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Photos, menus, letters, Comeback magazine, invitations, Cornell University Medical School Alumni Bulletin
    - Scrapbook C, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Clippings
    - Scrapbook C, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Letters, clippings, photos, cards
    - Scrapbook D, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Letters, programs, pertaining to the Budapest Conference
    - Scrapbook D: Certificate of Enlistment, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Scrapbook E, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Clippings, letters, programs
    - Scrapbook F (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Clippings, a reprint, U.S. Naval Institute proceedings
    - Scrapbook G: Hunterian Society Program, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Blue scrapbook, clippings
    - Scrapbook H, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Blue scrapbook, name on cover, article related to Kessler's receipt of the American Design Award (Apr 20, 1944)
- Series III. Photographs
  - Subseries IIIa. Medical Files
    - Traumatic Arteriovenous Fistula (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Drawing at operation before incision; man with paralysis of right arm; boy with crippled arm; crippled arms; 6 yr. old boy; right arm fitted with cineplastic prothesis; stump
    - Man with Stump (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Same man with prothesis, stump, stress on stump; hand holding box; brochure for cineplastic artificial arms; man with Kessler; stump
    - Artificial Arms (Box 2, Folder 3)
      2 photos of man hammering with artificial arms; stump; stump with tattoos, man hammering with artificial ars; man showing interchangeable tools, man with stump, prothesis
    - Crutch Makers (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Photo of operation, man painting, sawing; stump, arm showing injuries; prothesis; cineplastic arm for forearm amputation
    - Dorsal Motor to Prothesis (Box 2, Folder 5)
      3 application of dorsal motor to prothesis: 2 x-rays of bones, hand, hand mechanism
    - Artificial Arm (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Arm lifting chain, 2 x-rays of broken arm, 2 stumps
    - Margaret Craig (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Flail Elbow (Box 2, Folder 8)
      X-ray of flail elbow, 2 artificial arms
    - Stump (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Stump with arm, 2 artificial arms, 2 stumps
    - Loss of Arm (Box 2, Folder 10)
      4 stumps, infant with congenital loss of 1 arm; 2 girls with artificial arms, 2 model boats
    - Forearm Prothesis (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Boy with cineplastic forearm, 2 men with forearm prothesis
    - Forearm Prothesis (Box 2, Folder 12)
      5 forearm prothesis; stump at shoulder
    - Arm Prothesis (Box 2, Folder 13)
      2 arms with prothesis; 4 stumps
    - Stumps (4) (Box 2, Folder 14)
      4 stumps, young man, with and without legs
    - Man With and Without Arms (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - X-rays (Box 2, Folder 16)
      X-ray of legs, 8 stumps, 3 articifical arms
    - X-rays (Box 2, Folder 17)
      X-ray of legs, 4 stumps, 4 artificial arms
  - Subseries IIIb. Service Years
    - Valentine Party, Mare Island Hospital (5), 1945-02-13 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Dr. Kessler (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Kessler With Others at Mare Island (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Kessler in Shorts (with negative) (2) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Kessler With Others and Portrait of a Child, 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Photos of Kessler, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Kessler, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Travel Photos (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Kessler with other Officers, Patients, Mess, Sailors (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Kessler in Formation with Others at Mare Island, with Effigy of Tojo (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Unidentified Captain (3) (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Series IV. Diaries and Notebooks
  - "Italy," "Trip Book", Undated; Env - A (Box 1, Folder A)
    Maroon, Dec 2 - Dec 14 (no year)
  - "My Trip", 1949; Env - B (Box 1, Folder B)
    Black, Aug 6 - Sep 8; Hawaii, Japan, Hong Kong, Thailand
  - England, Germany, France, 1947-07-23-1947-09-08; Env - C (Box 1, Folder C)
    Brown leather
  - Trip to Rome, 1948-05-09-1948-06-11; Env - D (Box 1, Folder D)
    Green; account of Kessler's trip to Rome to present an exhibit of United States techniques to the meeting of the International College of Surgeons
  - "Travels", 1949-01-21-1949-07-30; Env - E (Box 1, Folder E)
    Deep purple; around the world
  - Yugoslavia Trip, 1951; Env - F (Box 1, Folder F)
    Miscellaneous medical notes
  - Miscellaneous Medical Notes, Env - G (Box 1, Folder G)
  - Medical Notes (Aug 12), Undated; Env - H (Box 1, Folder H)
  - Notes, 1930-12-23-1930-12-30; Env - I (Box 1, Folder I)
  - Address Book, Env - J (Box 1, Folder J)
- Series V. Works by Kessler
  - Subseries Va. Published Works
    - Bibliography of Articles (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Published Works, 1925-1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      "Treatment of Pneumonia with Diathermy" (1925), "The Curative Workshop and the Determination of the Capacity to Work" (1936), "Traumatic Appendicitis" (1938), "The Office Management of Low Back Pain" (1932), "Disability Evaluation Following Fracture", "Rehabilitation of the Amputee"
    - United Nations Technical Assistance Administration on a Mission to Yugoslavia, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Low Back Pain in Industry, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Report of Rehabilitation Mission to the Philippines", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Report of Rehabilitation of the Handicapped in the Philippines", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Collected Papers, 1937-1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Subseries Vb. Addresses
    - Addresses, 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      "Proceedings: Eastern Connecticut Conference on the Rehabilitation of Injured Workers" (1951), "Address to the International Society for the Welfare of Cripples" (1951), "Address given at the Dedication of the New Convalescent Wing of the Michael Reese Hospital" (Dec. 14, 1957), "Address at the First National Vocational Council in Israel" (Dec. 8, 1958), Proceedings of the Texas Employers Insurance Association Rehabilitation Symposium
- Series VI. Works about Kessler
  - Works about Kessler, 1952-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    People (Nov. 19, 1952), America (no. 17), United Nations Bulletin (Jan. 15, 1954, Vol. XVI no.2), United Hospital News (Vol. 1 no. 2, July 1959)
  - Works about Kessler, 1944-1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Cornell University Medical College Bulletin (Aug 1944), World Over (Jan 25, 1952), New Era (Vol. 1 no. 2 Mar. 1952), Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation (Vol. XXXIV no. 10, Oct. 1953)
  - Biography of Kessler (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Source unknown
- Series VII. Education Mementos
  - Commencement Exercises Program, Cornell University, 1916-06-21 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    The DeWitt Clinton High School Yearbook (1912)